There is a debate that never dies. It's
called calling dead. And today I sat
down with Jason Bay, CEO of Alban Squad.
He's trained sales team at Trippling
Gong and Shopify. [music] And in this
episode we look at the data. The average
rep books meetings on 4.56% [music]
of course. Top reps 20 to 35% and Jason
shares his calling structure. How to
open the call. How to talk about
problems instead of your product and
[music] how to sound like someone who
gets it. We also cover how A's can build
a weekly habit for Arbon and how to
coaches their teams one rep at a time.
This is how the best kitchens run.
Enjoy. Before we start, uh if you've
been following the show, listening to
the show for a while, you may have
noticed that I didn't publish any
episode for the past 6 months, but uh
the Arbon [music] Kitchen podcast is
back and I'm not coming the same way
with the show. We are making some
changes, new formats, live sessions,
[music] and some things I'm really
excited about. So, more converation
coming soon. Now, enjoy the episode.
Jason, there is always debate whether
cold calling is dead.
What does your data uh from working with
businesses and companies like Ripping,
Shopify, and Zoom tell us about coding
effectiveness in 2025?
>> I would say overall it it's less
effective than it was two years ago
even. It's much harder. Um, and I think
that when things start to get really
hard, when you don't have the soft
skills and the and the sort of minimum
bar of skills to make it work, a lot of
organizations aren't enabling around it
properly. So, there's a lot of people
that aren't able to book the meetings
that they need. And it's for a lot of
different reasons. But if I were to give
you some stats to kind of talk about it,
when we think about connect rates, you
know, the average connect rates about
5.4% 4% and it depends on industry,
right? But this is according to Gong
data, Gong in 30 minutes President's
Club. Yet, you'll see reps and
organizations that have like a 13 plus%
or 15 plus% connect rate. What you can't
get away with anymore is like, dude,
cell phone data and good accurate mobile
data, verifying the phone numbers,
making sure your dialer isn't showing up
as spam, like all of that stuff is like
infinitely more important because so
many fewer people pick up the phone. So,
it can feel a lot like, hey, people
don't pick up their phone these days.
The pickup rates are going down. And
that's absolutely true, but in order to
make it work, you have to be like in the
top 10 or 20 percentile to make it work.
Um, the average set rate for meetings is
about 4.6%.
And again, the above average teams are
going to have somewhere around 16, 17,
18%. I've worked with an organization uh
we helped them go from like 22 to 35%.
You know uh success rate on a connected
call to a qualified meeting. So it can
be done but to get an entire org to
convert at 15 20 25 plus percent like
that requires a lot of enablement. It
requires a lot of training. It requires
frontline leaders that really know what
they're doing. And most organizations,
this sort of hit them by surprise a year
or two ago when it seemed like people
stopped responding to emails and calls
and all of that kind of stuff. So, is
cold calling dead? No, it's it's not
dead. It's it's far from that, but it's
certainly as a whole less effective.
Like, I'd be lying to you if I didn't
say it was less effective than it was.
It's infinitely harder, but there are
still teams like Rippling, they're very
public about this. I mean, half of their
pipeline comes from outbound cold
calling.
>> Yeah, I agree with you on that. Um, also
just a stat about what you're saying
about the success rate. Um, I think it's
uh I don't know a lot of reps or
companies achieving this success rate.
We're going to unpack that today. But uh
I think uh yeah 30 20 plus% such percent
it's really like really like um top top
tier for for calls. If we go back to uh
code coding uh spec sorry connect rate
specifically I know some companies for
example coding uh cyber security for
cyber security products and they have
like 1% to 2% connect rate which is low
but that's the average for cyber
security and then you have like
companies like uh owner uh they call
restaurant owners and they have like 16%
connect rate with decision makers. So
obviously like you said depends on the
industry but for me like you said I
really think uh call coding it's you
have enablement what you say on the
phone but also the the upside the
operation side of call cing having the
right phone number and stuff like that
really make s your team successful
>> I don't know what the future of cold
calling is in enterprise calling cell
phone numbers I I think when you're in
the case of owner the SMB you know
rippling is a lot of SMB as well calling
into a business where you're calling
into a corporate line. There's going to
be a substantially higher pickup rate
when you do that, when you're not
calling direct cell phones. I don't know
what that's going to look like. If you
had to say 5 years, what's it going to
look like calling seuite executives on
their cell phones? I just see that
diminishing more and more over time.
That's going to be a harder and harder
and harder and harder thing to do. I
really see the phone being a tool to
help other things. So, for example, Um,
a couple weeks ago we just did a big
event in Austin, Texas where for a week
we hosted a sales uh executive dinner.
Uh, we did like a Iron Chef style event
for 25 sales execs. We got a couple
hundred people sign up for a rep
networking event. Um, I think doing
in-person stuff and having an offer like
that's the thing I feel that needs to be
upgraded with Outbound right now is you
got to really think about we've done the
volume thing. Yeah,
>> we've done that for the last decade with
all of the sales engagement platforms.
We've overwhelmed people with volume to
get their attention. The next thing we
need to start thinking about now is the
offer. What are we giving them in return
for their time? And a demo of your
product is just not enough. Um, I have a
client that sells ecom and the thing
that they do is, you know, they they
conduct a site audit before reaching out
to someone and they have tools on the
back end through AI and their marketing
team that like does the site audits
across all of their accounts for them.
and shows them the load time on the
website, right? They spend a minute
going through the checkout process. So,
they're experiencing the brand like they
have something to bring to that
conversation to share with the buyer
that is valuable. Another client of
mine, if you're thinking, hey, I sell
B2B and you know, I can't experience the
brand. Another client of mine, you know,
mystery shopped several hundred
companies in a category and they would
call them and share some of the findings
from the mystery shop, right? So,
there's all kinds of things that you can
do to like really think about what's the
value that I could share with them in
that first meeting. No different than
you wouldn't send someone to a landing
page unless you're famous. No one's
going to sign up on a landing page and
give you their name and phone number and
email unless they're going to get
something valuable in return. So this
same concept applies in marketing. When
someone goes to a landing page, they
need to get a high quality piece of
content in return. They need to get your
podcast, right? People are willing to
pay a subscription for your podcast
because it's so valuable. Now, I don't
think that many of the buyers that reps
are landing meetings with would pay any
amount of money for that meeting. Like
no money. I don't even think they would
give5 or $10 if they I think that that
would be a barrier for them actually.
There's just so little that is being
shared with them in that. So, so
rethinking the offer is pretty big and
and the phone is a tool to do that. You
can only have such a great talk track
and all of that kind of stuff. It's like
what are you giving the buyer in return
for their time?
>> Could you focus on the ecom example you
are giving? So, how would you use that
uh with coding? So,
do you use that in the opener or how do
you leverage that? The way that I think
of just to kind of set this up, Elrich,
the way that I think of the opener is
the average cold call lasts 80 seconds
according to Chorus, you're not going to
book a meeting in 80 seconds. So what
that means is that most cold calls fail
really in the first minute and it has a
lot to do with their first impression.
So if you believe that people don't pick
up cold calls on purpose, and I'm happy
to argue with anyone that does believe
that, uh people pick up these calls on
accident. They think that you're someone
else. So your first job is to
immediately get their attention. One of
the many ways that you can do that is
through a permissionbased opener. I
really like PBOS's. Um so I'm going to
inject this relevance into the
permissionbased opener. So I might say
something like, "Hey Elleric, it's Jason
was just on your website and tried to
add something to the card and it didn't
work. By the way, again, it's Jason with
XYZ company. You got a minute for me to
share the reason for my call." Or you
could say, uh, "Hey, Eric, it's Jason.
Was calling you because I was on a few
competitor sites and noticed that your
load speed was about four times longer
and could be impacting conversion rates.
Again, it's Jason with XYZ company. Can
I take a minute to share why I called
you specifically?"
There's a bunch of variations of that,
but the idea here is that in that
opener, I'm going to introduce myself
really quickly, but I'm not going to ask
how you're doing or how your day is
going. And and and that can vary by
region, by the way. You might need to be
a little bit more formal in AMIA, for
example, with pleasantries, but I want
to open right away with something that I
found out about them. And this is not
always going to be the case with, let's
say you're doing something that's SMB
that's highly transactional, you might
like kind of genericize the opener a
bit. And what you can do, uh, Kyle
shared this in your podcast I think at
owner is like they append data for the
rep on like the location or neighboring
stores that they or restaurants that
they might work with. And maybe I open
up with something like that. Uh, hey
Elrich, it's Jason. We're working with
uh, Taco Tuesdays down the street uh,
there in Austin. Again, it's Jason. You
got a minute for me to share why I
called you specifically? like any
variation of that where you're maybe
localizing it and doing it even a little
bit more at scale
um that like relevance in the beginning
of the opener is really really key.
>> Yeah. So for owners specifically I know
they use this social proof in the opener
and then um for in terms of relevancy
obviously they're going after SMB. So
it's not like you can go online find
like an interview of the CEO of the
owner of the the restaurant. So what
they but what they use they have the
website of the restaurant in front of
them um and they know if for example
they use uh Uber it's um third party
delivery tools uh and they know if owner
could be relevant and depending on the
traffic they have on the website or for
example if they use Uber they can adapt
their um their messaging bas on the
stuff. So it's SMB but you can still
find clues about what they do and how
you can focus on because if they don't
use about it where basically owner they
need to educate them on online ordering
for their restaurants versus well
they're already doing it. So it's more
like um have you thought about building
your own website and using uh your own
website to to drive orders instead of
using like a third party tool that
basically cost you 30% of uh your order.
Oh
>> yeah. So if we were using that as an
example, that would kind of be the next
part of the call that we could work in
is what I call the reverse pitch.
>> Okay.
>> So it's a permission based opener. And
if you're listening to this or watching
this and you're thinking, well, I don't
know. I don't like permission based
openers. Again, I have some data for
you. This is from Gong and 30 Minutes
President's Club. 100,000 plus cold
calls that they've analyzed. When you
ask people, did I catch you at a bad
time versus how's it going? versus using
some sort of permission based opener.
You can, you know, literally have two to
four times the amount of success on a
call by using a great permission based
opener. So, it's not the only way to
open your call, but it's very effective.
Before you you you go you go with the
first pitch, uh I have data too, but
from Nukes specifically. So, Nukes, they
they have data on the permissionbased
opener opener specifically. And what
they found, you have 53% of top reps,
they don't use permission based opener,
but they use context. And then you have
41%
using a permission based opener with
context. Basically, you have 95% using
context. And then you have like half
permission based opener, half they don't
use permission based open. Cold calling
is so funny to me because there's a data
element to this, but there's also a soft
skills art form of this that's just like
just being a good conversationalist
helps a lot on the phones, too. And you
you can't discount that. Um, so if we
think about the opener, the the next
part of the opener is what I call a
reverse pitch. So, where reps makes the
most common mistakes here is they start
to talk a lot about their product and
they start to get really solution
focused. And what I want to do is the
reverse of that. I want to talk about
the problems that people like them are
having. When you do this, when you use
problem based language, again, same
study from gone, you you will have a 16%
success rate of booking a meeting versus
a 5.5% success rate using product
buzzwords and that sort of stuff. The
way that this might sound is um Eric,
yeah, thank you for taking the call.
Again, the reason I was reaching out to
you is we're actually working with
several business owners in the Seattle
YA area, and the number one thing that
we're hearing right now is that they
want to add an ecom component to their
business, but it's just so complicated
with all of the tooling, limited staff,
all of that kind of stuff. They don't
really have a way to really open up
their sales outside of their local
region. I'm curious, is that something
you're thinking about or working on
right now? So, I'm giving the problem.
I'm speaking in customer voice. I'm not
saying Eric uh at XYZ company we help
business owners like you through uh ecom
whatever suite product platform thing do
this thing it's no don't do any of that
what you want to say is the top two
things that you hear every one of their
customers talking about and just before
you you move to the other example so
could you share a bit more context about
what this specific problem because just
like to understand because I know I'm
not familiar with the e-commerce
business fab space. So, could you give
more details about that?
>> Yeah. So, if you're a business owner and
you're running a small business and
let's say that you're uh running, I
don't know, you sell athletic apparel,
right? You have to compete against all
of these other bigname brands, Northace,
Columbia, whatever those brands are in
America and across the world, right? So,
in order to compete with them, if you if
you just have a brickandmortar presence,
you're losing out on all of the online
sales that you could get, but you're
also not adding all of these modern ways
that people like to buy and interact
with brands. For example, if I can't buy
something online and then pick up in
store or return in store, if your
competitor does that, I'm just going to
buy from them instead.
That's how much of like a red ocean it
is right now with like retail and ecom.
So the business owners are thinking
about how do I stay ahead and have this
technology but I don't have people in
house that are the equivalent of a
Salesforce admin right or a revops team.
I don't have that as a small business.
So it's how do they compete? That's
really the big thing. The next example
I'll give you just because it's more of
like an enterprise B2B example that I
think will be relevant to a lot of
people is I have a customer that sells a
contact center solution like one of
their customers is Target for example.
Um the irony is that these support
centers they have phone numbers on their
website but they don't want people to
call in because when you call in and I
have to talk to you that's really
expensive. If I could talk to you
through chat, even better if I can do it
through AI or I can just have you answer
your own question through an FAQ page.
That's cheap. That's what I want to do.
So, if I was calling a contact center
leader, it might sound something like,
you know, hey, Eric, it's Jason. Uh, was
on the FAQ page and I noticed that
you're pushing customers a lot to self-s
serve on the website right now. Uh, by
the way, it's Jason again with XYZ
company. You got a minute for me to
share why I called you specifically?
Person will say yes. U, awesome. Like I
said, I was on the FAQ page and in
speaking with a lot of contact center
leaders at companies like your targets
and Nordstrom's of the world, one thing
that they're sharing with us is that
they want to reduce the cost to serve,
but those FAQ pages and the chat bots
and all of that stuff for whatever
reason is actually creating more
frustration with customers and they end
up calling in anyways and they're not
able to identify the reasons why they
call in. I'm curious, how does that
resonate with you and and what you're
seeing at ABC company? Now, I could
punch that up even more if it's
enterprise and if I did research using
AI, let's say, through their 10Ks or 10
Q's, I could say, "Hey, I was calling
because I noticed one of the initiatives
was um to increase response time and
increase brand loyalty with your
customers and I saw this thing going
on." So, I could punch it up even more,
but that's kind of the general approach
of do some sort of relevance uh
permissionbased opener. I like the PBO's
and then I'm going to do a reverse pitch
where I'm going to speak through the
language of the customer. And
oftentimes, if you nail that, that
language right there, I've immediately
disarmed the prospect because they're
like, "Oh yo, this person talks to
people like me." And then naturally, the
next question you're going to get is,
"Well, what do you do now? Now I'm in
the driver's seat. They've asked me what
I do versus me having to pitch up.
>> Yeah. And what I like about that is you
are it's hard to say I'm not interested
because you are focusing on challenges
or problems them they're currently
facing. So and also you have and on top
of that you you've done some research.
It's not like just you you say one
problem but it's you've done your
research and then you leverage that in
Yep.
>> in the first 60 seconds of the call.
>> Yep. And you have to do that especially
if it's enterprise or strategic type of
sales. You're gonna have to come in with
something unique to that individual or
that company
>> also. Um and now how do you
approach color coding when for example
we are talking about Shopify order or
how do you approach when you have a
well-known brand versus some a brand
that no one knows on the phone? We
definitely cannot discount that when
you're calling from a brand like Shopify
or Ripling for example. Like it helps to
have that brand notoriety. It absolutely
does. You cannot discount that. Um what
you need to be conscious of when you
call from a brand like that is people
will put you into a bucket.
>> Yes.
>> So I dealt with this with I won't
mention the company name but they sell a
video communication solution and when
they would call people people would say
we already have we're already using your
solution. Right. So you need to like
anticipate objections.
>> Yes. So, you have to build that into
your opener. So, like if I was calling
for that video communications company, I
might say, "Hey, it's Jason from XYZ
company. Uh, I know you're already set
up with our video solution. A lot of our
customers are having challenges with and
XYZ, do you have a minute for me to walk
you through it?" Like, you have to
anticipate objections and build it into
your talk track. On the other hand, when
you don't have any brand notoriety, you
have to like be super super good on
talking about the problem. Like that
language that I used in the reverse
pitch, you have to nail that. If you
nail that, people don't give a what
the company is. They really don't care.
If you show them that, hey, I'm a
credible person and I speak with people.
Like, that's everything. How do you get
to that level? There's a couple
different ways. If you're an SDR, uh,
you need to be listening into sales
calls. If they don't record it, you need
to write shotgun with some of your reps.
Like, I literally want you to word for
word take the words that the customers
are using. Like, you're going to see
prominent patterns across people in the
same job titles and personas and
industries. You can even with those
sales calls, if they're being recorded,
you can download the transcripts, upload
it into Chat GBT, have Chat GBT help you
find those patterns. There's there's
just no excuse anymore not to know. Even
if you were starting with nothing, you
could have deep research on chat GBT
probably help you find a lot of this
stuff. But I want to get it in the
customer's language. If I'm an account
executive, the biggest hack is to center
your cold calling blocks to focus them
around people that you're running sales
calls with. So if I just did a sales
call yesterday with a VP of contact
center, I'm just literally in the opener
going to say, I was talking to a VP of
contact center at a retailer yesterday
and they shared XYZ challenge. I'm just
going to literally use the words that
they shared.
Is that relevant for you? It's like
you're doing so many things in that
moment. Like you're sharing that you
understand their problem. You're
demonstrating social proof. It's
relevant. It's like it's all of those
things.
So think about how can I as an account
executive take things I'm picking up
from the sales process and move it
forward into the outbound motion.
Use that same messaging, that same
language.
>> Yeah. And I love this approach because
um actually if all the companies I
worked at when I was still a rep that's
the one thing I was doing is trying to
listen
not customer that were closing but more
like the first demo and because on the
first five minutes most of the time they
say they're explaining why they're on
the call and they're explaining what the
problem they are facing and they they
they're looking for a solution and you
can leverage exactly the word they're
using for that. So,
>> 100%. Yeah, they're giving you the
language. That's the coolest part is the
language. You don't have to make it up.
>> Um, if I could make one more point on
this, seller, because I think it's
really important. The mindset behind
this approach is very important. Um, if
you can't see me, I'm basically on on
one side of the screen here saying this
is your world
>> where you sell stuff, your solution, all
of it exists in the world. On this side,
on the other side is your buyer's world.
When you do outbound, they didn't come
to you asking for information on your
product or service. You have to meet
them in their world first. You have to
speak in a language that they
understand. The mutual language between
buyer and seller is their priorities,
their problems. You bring them over this
to the solution later on in the sales
process. You do not do that during the
outbound process. You have to meet them
in their world. And that's what this is
all about is the quickest way to add
context to what you do is to explain it
through their problems.
That's how you add context really really
quickly. If we if we think about just
context specifically uh I learned
something also because I used to work at
chili pepper and chili paper they're
very famous for the scaling parts uh
that you can embed on your website
and I always had like the mindset of how
we were talking to marketing leaders
versus other personas and like a year
ago I was working with a company and I
was selling a solution internally for
this specific use case and when I was
talking to the CEO of the company, he
didn't care about the same things about
the marketing dealers.
>> Yeah.
>> But something that clicked with him
specifically was when I started to talk
about competitors because competitors of
his company were using similar solutions
and when I start talking about the his
competitors that's when he started okay
maybe we should figure out this
solution. And I say okay like that's
interesting to to have like different
perspective because it's not because for
marketing leaders they might care about
a few things but specifically this year
and I think others might care more about
competitor versus the marketing about
the drop off on demo requests for
example
>> back to what I brought up originally at
the beginning when like when you think
about ways to get someone's attention
there was the volume we talked about
offer the next one is relevance and this
is that's where that fits into the
relevance bucket.
It's the buyer's priorities. It's their
problems. It's their competitors. It's
what's going on in their industry. Like
if I can really contextualize things for
them, that's another great way to get
people's attention.
>> Yes. Uh now let's focus on if I'm a
leader uh SDR leader or VP of sales and
if yeah they could f only focus on
improving one elements of their team's
called coding. What would drive the
biggest results? I think the biggest
thing is and it depends on where you're
getting started from. Let's like use a
common example of let's say you're
trying to get your AES to do more
self-sourcing and you're and they're not
doing a lot of it right now. What I
refer to what we call outbound squad is
the weekly rhythm.
>> Okay,
>> that's what you want to develop first.
The weekly rhythm is the equivalent of
if we're trying to make exercise a
habit. Let's just get to the gym on a
regular basis. Let's just let's before
we optimize the workout and the meal
plan, let's let's just make sure we're
exercising regularly. Y
>> So the weekly rhythm is you want to
really think about habit snacking.
>> So instead of creating new things for
you and your reps to do, let's just bolt
things into the consistent uh stuff
that's happening every week already.
Every sales manager is likely doing a
one-on-one with their rep and they're
likely doing a weekly team meeting.
There's likely some sort of all hands
call. There's monthly business reviews.
there's QBRs. So, how can we insert pipe
genen and outbound into the existing
meetings that we already have? So, with
one-on- ones, for example, a part of the
prep that a rep should do prior to their
one-on-one is pick out the accounts that
they're going to outbound into that week
and they need to bring that into the
meeting. They need to bring in and
brainstorm messaging that they might
use, calls them when they're making
their calls. Um, their team meetings,
you need to talk about cold calling in
the team meetings. pull recordings from
reps doing this stuff. Report on call
activity. Create some sort of
scoreboard. Like you have to start, it
starts with just talking about it on a
regular basis. So that's the big thing.
Uh the second thing is from an
enablement standpoint, what you can
start to think about is well, what kind
of coaching culture am I creating around
calls? And one simple habit is a rep
brings a recorded call into every
one-on-one that they've already tried to
self- diagnose and coach. what they
would have done differently in that
call. Manager listens to that call
beforehand. Rep listens to that call
beforehand. And now there's a coaching
moment every Monday meeting that is
happening prior to that meeting. Right?
So creating this coaching uh coaching
culture rather
super super important. So if I was just
getting started like those are the
basics you have to start by doing at
least that
>> and uh okay so let's say that was for
the a side. and let's do on the SDR
side.
>> So with BDRs, I'm going to make the
assumption that they're probably already
making calls on a weekly basis and they
may or may not be doing well. So I think
with um outbound calling, what you need
to do is get really granular with how
you provide the coaching. So I like to
think of the call, we've only talked
about the intro of the call. I like to
think of the intro of the call, there's
the hook, and there's the close. prior
to even getting on the call. There's the
amount of call activity and there's the
pickup rates. So, what we want to think
about is like if you had to look at some
metrics, you want to use metrics to
diagnose what each individual rep needs
help with. Is it an activity problem?
So, are they even making enough calls to
hit the meeting target? In which case,
that's a time management issue, right?
How do we get them to block this off and
then hold them accountable to doing it?
One hack that I would recommend, I call
it the midweek check-in. Most managers
do a one-on-one on Monday and they just
forget about the reps until the next
Monday and they say, "Did you hit your
targets?" And they say no. And then it's
just like the same weekly cycle. You
should be checking on a daily basis or
at the very minimum on Wednesday. You
should be doing a check-in with reps
that aren't halfway towards their
activity target yet. So activity,
there's connect rates next. So connect
rates, there's an operational component
to this that is like workflow related
that is entirely up to the rep. They can
only work with the data that they have,
but making sure, hey, are they calling
cell phone numbers? Um, have we run a
report in our sales engagement tool or
our dialer if we're using Nooks and have
we showed reps when the highest pickup
rate opportunities are and are we having
reps make calls at those times? are
those reps calling people, opening the
emails, like doing all of the basic
things to drive pickup rate.
So once we have pickup rate and connect
rate, if that's not the issue, then we
can start to look at, well, what happens
in the call? How long does the call
last? What's the conversion rate of
those calls? So if we look and this rep
has shorter average talk time, let's say
per call than other reps, we know that's
probably an intro based problem. So,
let's pull some recordings of let's
let's see if we need to drill that
permission based opener like how many uh
a lot of uh organizations will measure
the number of conversations. So, a
pickup they'll treat as someone that
says hello. A conversation will be a
call that lasts longer than 60 seconds
or 90 seconds, let's say. So, if you
have that extra metric, you can even
then dial in with that rep. Do I need to
focus on the PBLO and intro or do I need
to focus on the questions maybe they ask
during the hook? So I can dial it in on
an even more granular level from there.
And then lastly, the last metric would
be show rate of those meetings that they
set. So if the show rate is below, in my
opinion, 75%
75% is world class. 75 80% show rate to
outbound set meetings over the phone. If
it's below that, we need to talk about
how they're confirming on the calls, the
confirmation process, the emails that we
send before with the agenda of the
calendar invites, the title, etc. Um,
but we need to get super granular and
for you BDR teams like it needs to be
rep byrep coaching where you're looking
at the stats on that granular of a level
giving individualized coaching and
feedback to the rep.
>> For calling specifically if they are
really good on connect on the connect
rate and number of dials. Um something
you can also add is in the call
disposition in your dialer you talk to
the prospect they hang up you can
mention the technical disposition and
then in your call disposition you might
have like 15 disposition but uh for call
going specifically it's helpful in your
reports because you can see pretty uh
quickly where you are your calls are
ending and then it's quicker also for
self coaching but also for the manager
also uh to to really focus on the
important part of the car. I'm curious
for you, what are some of the
dispositions that when you're working
with clients that you have them add that
they aren't already using?
>> The first step is accuracy. So, are you
talking to the right person? Um, if they
pick up or for example, if the call is
disconnected right away, so you know
that's the number is disconnected. So,
you know that's not the right number and
we do that just to measure the accuracy
from the provider. Then for the data
team up team, it's g give them details
about which data provider is good or
not. uh and then having like we're
talking about um operation so you can
think about using different data
providers and then the ops team they can
provide another phone number for for
this specific prospect so that's one is
a pick up the phone uh is it phone
number um I know there is tools to give
you this information but sometimes you
don't have it so is it a cell phone
number or the the headquarter like we
are talking about earlier corporate
phone number that's another
Uh because if you want to focus on the
right phone number, obviously direct
phone numbers are the phone numbers.
That's one. Um if it's the right person,
did did you uh re did you say your
permission based opener yes or no? Did
they say yes? And because if they say
no, that's a disposition. And so
obviously you can measure the fitness of
your permission based opener. Then you
have another one also for um you set the
hook for example for you that will be
the hook and then you have the closing
part. So you can see basically the
conversion rate from each step in your
coing process.
>> How do you make sure that the reps are
accurately inputting the extra stuff
because this is like the did I do a
permission based opener or not like the
hook like it seems like a lot of that I
don't know if Nooks does this. Is it
able to use AI to detect whether or not
reps are using that sort of stuff?
>> That's a good question. I don't know if
they can do that. Uh I used so that's
the only one I have experience with. So
we were doing that manually. So you have
uh permission to uh to p permission to
pitch depending on the the the
disposition you're using and so you have
like a drop down with everything. Uh you
need to train them on that obviously. Um
so that's
sometime it's accurate but most of the
time it's accurate. I know. I imagine
some at some point with AI it will be
possible to uh automate that because
that will be quicker and it's market. So
>> yeah, that's going to be pretty cool
because
>> yeah,
>> anything that's like manually inputed.
I've just seen so many horror stories,
you know, with that. But I I love the
data quality thing too where you
disposition and then if you have the
lead source attached to that contact
like your RevOps team, you could
probably create some sort of automation
with Clay or something like that where
it just automatically adds another
number. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Exactly. because uh the topic
where I'm hearing a lot about calling
specifically it's uh oh yeah clay is
better than zoom in for cognism for
example for data quality
the problem with clay uh in general it's
they have like 60% accuracy on phone
numbers and then zoom in for cognism
they have like 75 plus%
uh cognism have 80% something like that
so
I don't think clay is better than zoom
in for or cognism but
the accuracy. That's one thing you need
to measure. But the other thing is
what's the match rate of your prospect
inside the database of those tools and
and unfortunately and I don't think you
have like one tool to do everything.
It's you need to combine a few of them
and some tools are they have great phone
numbers but some some other they don't.
Earlier you were talking about top
repres
but you said top reps they have like um
a booking rate
between 20 to 30% uh from conversation
to meeting booked what are they doing
differently
>> I think the first thing and again you
cannot discredit this is the soft skills
>> y
>> it's the tonality it's it's how I sound
on the phone doing these it's do you
sound like you've done this hundreds or
thousands of times
So either through experience or through
a lot of practice they sound smooth.
They have good tonality. They annunciate
their words. They don't talk too fast.
Like they they are good
conversationalists.
Like that's number one. Uh number two is
really the industry expertise around
like really understanding and being able
to articulate the problem. You can't
speak in customer voice if you don't
really understand the problem. And
there's just no excuse anymore for that.
I mean as a BDR you can have three
months of career experience and through
Chad GBT and all these AI platforms and
through like you can learn everything
that you need to know about the buyer's
problems. So articulating the problem is
really big when it comes to that second
part of the call the hook. The idea here
with the hook is that I don't believe
that just because you say hey are do you
have these problems and the person says
yes that you just go in to set a meeting
like you you have to dig into that a
little bit more. And the reason for that
is like no, you're not going to find
this like huge impactful problem in a
five or seven minute call. But what you
are going to do is build a relationship
and build rapport with this person. So
you cannot discount the fact that the
more time I have them on the phone, the
more likely they are to book a meeting
and the more likely they are to show up.
So with the hook, I need to have what we
refer to as money questions. So a muddy
question is a good problem-based
question that really reveals some sort
of gap in what they have right now. So
if I was using the contact center, one
thing that they know customers can't do
is they're not collecting, you know,
data from all of the customerf facing
conversations through text, email, chat,
etc. and then spoon feeding those
insights to tell them where customers
are getting stuck and where the friction
is and why they decide to call into the
contact center. So a question I might
ask and the framework here is I call it
question stacking. So with these money
questions I want to stack context in
front of the question before I ask it. I
don't want to ask a question like what's
your biggest challenge with XYZ. I want
to say, "Hey, I'm really curious about
what you mentioned with the FAQ pages."
Cuz oftent times what we see is that
customers are not extracting info from
the DMs, the text, the phone calls, etc.
that they're having with their users.
And because they're not able to get that
information, it's really hard to
identify patterns and reasons why
customers are calling in. How are you
collecting information like that to
prevent people from calling in? Oh,
we're relying on post surveys.
Interesting. Again, I hear that a lot.
with postc customer surveys. Our stats
show us that only 6% of customers even
take those surveys and it's usually the
vocal minority of folks. How are you
capturing feedback from the 94% of
customers that don't respond to those
surveys?
And it's like
they're never going to give you a good
answer to that, right?
>> Yeah.
>> And that becomes the reason to me. That
becomes the part where I can close. So,
uh, great worldclass reps are very good
at asking questions. They don't do deep
discovery in the call, but they do some
discovery. They expose a problem. They
use that as the reason to meet. The
other thing that they're really good at
is getting people to show up to the
meeting. So, the average show rate to a
a meeting set from a cold call according
to Gong, and I see something very
similar, it's about 56%.
Um, the best reps are going to have
somewhere between 70 to 80% show rate or
higher uh to those meetings. So, there's
a couple really simple things that you
can do in the call to minimize the
chance that someone doesn't show up. Uh,
one of them is getting them to confirm
the calendar invite on the call. And the
reason why this is so important is if
the person is using Gmail or Outlook,
oftent times if you send them an invite,
it doesn't hit their calendar unless
they accept it from within their email,
especially these enterprise accounts.
So, I'm just going to say, Eric, um, I
just sent you an invite for 2 p.m.
tomorrow. Would you mind? and I want to
make sure it didn't go to spam. Would
you mind hitting accept on that real
quick? I'll give you a couple seconds to
do that. I just wait for them to accept
it or make small talk with them while
you're doing that.
>> Um I want to reconfirm the purpose of
the call. So the purpose of the call is
not to get a demo of my platform. It's
um hey again so you mentioned that
you're looking to reduce the cost to
serve. Uh you want fewer people calling
into the contact center. We'll talk a
little bit more about that problem and
also how we're helping Nordstrom tackle
a similar problem. Uh if it makes sense,
we'll talk about how and if we might be
able to help. Uh you're going to be
speaking with Elrich. Uh he's my account
executive. He's actually got seven,
eight years of experience working with
real retail brands like yours. So he's
going to be able to talk about a lot of
the patterns that we're seeing in
contact centers. And I sent you that
invite. Um, you should get a
confirmation email maybe later today or
first thing tomorrow with like a case
study from our work with Nordstrom and a
few other things and that's it. So, one
of the things that I want to do as an
SDR especially is I want to hype up my
AE. I want to talk about them and
humanize them. Right? When you humanize
people, people for the most part don't
like to be jerks. So if if you humanize
the people that they're going to be
meeting with, it's harder to not show up
when I feel like I'm bailing on a human
versus some random person I've never met
before. Something else also why they
have like a high short rate for what
specifically you mentioned is they have
a reason to be on the call. It's not
like they're curious about your
solution. um because curious just to
learn more about solution I think it's
enough to to be on a call but uh you
have some challenges that you have
identified but also you talk about the
AE and the expertise of this A for this
specific industry I think also it's
another layer uh that
um they know that they will talk to
someone that understand their their
situation
>> 100% I call it like you know you're
you're basically setting up a blind date
for your AE so if you're setting up a
blind date for your friend, you would
hype up your friend. You talk about how
awesome they are, right? And how good of
a time that they're going to have.
You're setting up a blind date for
someone that they've never met before.
So, you got to hype them up a bit.
>> Earlier, you were talking about AI. Um,
so how who are you or the team you are
currently training incorporating AI into
call coding? Uh, it could be preparation
or execution in 2025.
>> Preparation really is where most of this
is happening.
>> Uhhuh.
>> We call it reason to meet. So, this is
going to mostly apply to enterprise or
mid-market reps that have to do research
prior to calling to someone. Um, if you
think about a traditional account plan,
most reps when they build an account
plan, it takes them hours to do. They
spend hours researching. They spend all
this time Elrich researching and like
this amount of time actually speaking
with people. So, it's like the complete
inverse of what you want to do. Let's
spend all of this time researching
companies most of which are never going
to respond to me. So you need to kind of
flip that on its head. Um our AI sort of
framework that we think about is um
prompt dig summarize. So if I was doing
account research for outbound for
example, I need a prompt that's going to
really like I can show chat GPT or
Gemini or whatever I'm using. Hey,
here's what I sell. Here's who I sell it
to. Here's the problems that they have.
Um here's what I want you to find. You
know, scrape through their 10Ks, 10Ks,
etc. look for problems specifically
related to uh demand gen lead generation
uh new products coming out etc. Like you
need to like prompt it on exactly what
you wanted to look for. The dig is the
AI is not perfect. We could run chat GBT
side by side with the same exact
searches and we'll get different
results. So we need to dig and we need
to be able to tell it hey this is not
specific enough or this is this is
related. I want you to dig into it more.
This is unrelated. And then the
summarize, we need to have a way that we
can prompt it to just quickly summarize
everything it's giving me. So, we've got
it pretty dialed in with most of our
customers that sell midmarket or
enterprise where it'll do an enterprise
account plan in like five minutes and
spit out a a fairly good personalized
email which has got talking points that
you could use in a cold call. Um, the
other really underrated thing too is uh
you need to get chat GBT on your phone
and be paying for the advanced version
because you can role play back and forth
with it and it's better than any of the
roleplay solutions that I've seen in the
market. There's one I won't mention the
name. They keep bugging me about like
partnering with them and I'm like I I
called their AI robot and couldn't even
book a meeting with a sales leader. I'm
like you guys I'm pretty good at cold
calling, okay? So, if I can't book a
meeting with my own persona, like
there's something off about this. And it
felt really robotic, uh, chat GPT is
such a great tool to be able to like
roleplay back and forth with out loud.
It's it's really dialed in. You can have
it ramp up the difficulty. You can
practice specific objections. I mean,
it's it's a really really good
>> Yes. Um, so what you mention, I'm going
to start with the prompt for the
research specifically. um using the
specific pain points you can solve. It's
key for the problem because AI for HTP
in general or B2 they are not good
enough yet to understand the pain points
uh that you're solving. Um so you need
to be specific about that for your
research. And then the other thing uh
that's good about the pump you mentioned
is sometimes I was seeing people saying
oh yeah if they have a 10k
somewhere the 10k and they have a a
summary of the 10k but it's not specific
for their product. So yes you have a
summary of your 10k but is it specific
enough for for you to reach out to
someone and document? No. So exactly
what you're saying h you can do that
with the 10k you can do that with 10q
also um interviews videos and stuff like
that I know right now with I'm using
perplexity I think better for for the
research actually thanp but actually is
getting better with deep research and um
I'm pretty surprised uh they are they
pick up pretty quickly against
perplexity so I'm using I'm trying both
to see the result of both but the deep
research really allow you to have like
um doing AI the research on top of
executive of the account also on top of
the 10K and it's amazing. If we go back
to the role play, you mentioned about a
DPT. Um, I was playing with it and yeah,
it's it's amazing because um it's really
well trained I would say in ter
>> you need to obviously
>> because uh you need to use your
framework uh to train it and then uh um
I created a prompt to do that. So you
have like the cold coding role play, but
then you have uh the uh the AI, they can
give you feedback about your your role
play. So I think yeah, it's great for
for coing.
>> Yeah, it's it's
I mean it's so much better than role
playing with a person because you can
tell it how difficult you want it to be.
You can tell it to pretend to be the CMO
at XYZ company that you're reaching out
to. I mean, you could tell it to
realistically do a lot of those things.
It's pretty cool.
>> I know there is one too specifically
that K mentioned on on on the podcast
that they use AI and they basically you
can use your own calls to train the the
AI model. So the AI is not like um
making up stuff. it's using a real
conversation and so you can practice
with this and I think that's yeah next
level to do that because it's not like
>> uh train on it's really strain on your
situation so
>> if you had to compress all your
calculing wisdom into three
non-negotiable principles what would
they be
>> oh man three non-negotiable principles I
think uh one of them is the habit is
more important than the outcome this is
just like exercise just like eating
healthy, the habit of doing this on a
regular basis is way more important than
how that call block went. So, you got to
make sure to do that. Um, the second one
would be customer voice over product
voice. When in doubt, I'm always going
to speak from the voice of the customer
about their problems, etc.
Um, lastly,
I don't want to like I want to be
mindful of
the connection between how I interact
with people in my personal life and and
my professional life. And the and the
point that I'm making here is that a lot
of people transform into a different
human when they cold call or when they
hop on sales calls. They start talking
like this and they're like, "Hey, Rick."
You know, they they talk like they're
talking to a little kid or a dog or
something, right? They use uptalk,
customer voice, etc. So treat them like
a human. You're talking with another
human like you need to be
conversational, keep it casual, not
unprofessional, but keep it casual and
conversational. It's going to serve you
really well. So we are talking about
practicing specifically and practicing I
think it's underestimated for coing
specifically and the other day I was uh
recording a webinar with a French
company actually no with cognism for the
French market and we are talking about
why you need to practice for coording
and not just expecting to be good on the
phone without practicing and so uh I
think practicing we don't talk about it
enough
>> I mean this is a way that you can have
really structured practice is because
with the pickup rates being so low um
you get very few opportunity. It's not
like you're most people if you're not
using a dialer you're not having dozens
of conversations on the phone every week
you get very little time to actually get
your repetitions in. So you have to
practice with AI or with a partner or do
something.
>> Yeah. And actually the push back I had
in France is because the connect rate in
France is way higher than in the US. In
France some companies have like 30 plus
connect rate. So that's why they say,
"Yeah, I'm practicing with uh my
prospect because that you need to
practice with your prospect if you want
to be good."
Yes and no. I I don't think you
shouldn't
practice on your on your prospect. You
should do both, actually.
>> Yeah, you definitely need to do both,
but I'll tell you what, I'd rather have
reps that have a bias towards calling
prospects than not calling [music]
prospects.
>> Oh yeah, man. There is hope. Jason,
we're already at the end of the
recording. So, uh, if anyone want to
learn more about you or Outbound Squad,
what's the best way uh to be in?
>> Yeah, outboundsquad.com
is going to be [music] the best place.
So, you're going to find links to a
bunch of free resources there. We have a
podcast as well. [music] Go check it
out. Outbound Squad Podcast. Um, I post
free content every day on LinkedIn. And
if you're a sales leader looking to get
help [music] implementing some of the
stuff that we talked about for your team
or for your SDRs for your AEES or you're
making an outbound pivot in your
organization and want AES to do more
self-sourcing, whatever it might be, you
can hit us up there as well. So outbound
squad.com is the best place to to learn
about us.
>> Perfect. Thank you so much for being on
the show and for everyone listening. I
see you on the next episode.